Department of Kinesiology. Minutes of Committees and Staff Meetings. 1929-1978.
UCLA Library Special Collections
Department of Kinesiology. Minutes of Committees and Staff Meetings.
1929-1978
University Archives Record Series 334
UCLA Library Special Collections
1.2 linear ft. (3 boxes)
Record Series 334 contains minutes of meetings held by committees and staff of UCLA's Department of Kinesiology.
Department of Kinesiology
Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Historical Note
The Department of Kinesiology trace its origins to the Department of Physical Education established in 1915 as part of the Los Angeles State Normal School. In 1919 the department became part of the Teachers College of the Southern Branch, with separate departments for men and women. During the 1920s, the department's efforts were devoted to the training of Physical Education teachers and the administration of the Physical Education classes that were required of all undergraduates. In 1932 the Men's and Women's Gymnasiums were completed. In 1938 the M.S. degree in Physical Education was authorized. In 1939 the department became part of the newly established College of Applied Arts. In 1952 separate divisions for men and women were eliminated. In 1960 the College of Applied Arts was dissolved and replaced by the College of Fine Arts. The Physical Education Department was then transferred to the College of Letters and Science, Division of Life Sciences. In 1962 the revised physical education major was approved and focused on Kinesiology (the science of human movement) and one of three allied fields: physiology, psychology, or sociology. In 1973 the department changed its name to Kinesiology. When Donald T. Hardy retired in 1976, he was recognized as the founding father of the Kinesiology department. The department first offered a Ph.D. degree in Kinesiology in 1979. In 1990 the Kinesiology Department changed its name to the Physiological Sciences Department.
Since 1937 the chairmanship of what is now called the Physiological Sciences Department has been held successively by Frederick W. Cozens (1937-39), John F. Bovard (1939-47), Carl Haven Young (1947-52), Ben W. Miller (1952-62), Donald T. Handy (1962-1975), Jack F. Keogh (1975-1978), Serena E. Arnold (1978-1980), Judith L. Smith (1980-1985), V. Reggie Edgerton (1985-1989), Ronald F. Zernicke (1989-1992), Jack L. Feldman (1993- )
Scope and Content
Record Series 334 contains minutes of meetings held by committees and staff of UCLA's Department of Kinesiology. Files include meeting minutes of the following: staff meetings for the men's and women's divisions of the Physical Education Department (1932-1978), Advisory Committee (1948-1953), Counseling and Guidance Committee (1949-1951), Curriculum Committee, Physical Education and Military Affairs Committee (1944-1951), and several other committees.
This is an inactive record series; no additional University records are expected to be added.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 3466861
- Advisory committee., 1948-1953. (Box 1)
- Chancellor's committee on Department of Physical Education., 1954-1955. (Box 1)
- Community laboratory experiences committee., 1952. (Box 1)
- Coordinating committee, women., 1953-1954. (Box 1)
- Counseling and guidance committee., 1949-1951. (Box 1)
- Courses committee., 1948-1952. (Box 1)
- Curriculum committee. Lower division., 1949-1950. (Box 1)
- Curriculum coordinating council., 1950-1958. (Box 1)
- Curriculum studies committee., 1946-1950. (Box 1)
- Graduate committee., 1929-1950. (Box 1)
- Liason committee on physical education., 1953-1957.; 2 folders (Box 1)
- Observation committee., 1951. (Box 1)
- Physical education and military affairs committee., 1944-1951. (Box 1)
- Physical education reorganization committee., 1937-1938. (Box 1)
- Secondary school affiliation committee., 1948-1950. (Box 1)
- Sports Recreation Pavillion committee., 1959-1962. (Box 1)
- Staff meetings. Joint. Materials and minutes., 1949-1951. (Box 2)
- Staff meetings. Materials and minutes., 1957-1960.; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Staff meetings. Men's department. Materials and minutes., 1932-1940; 1942-1950.; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Staff meetings. Schedule and calendars., 1956-1974. (Box 2)
- Staff meetings. Women's department. Materials and minutes., 1937-1938; 1940-1951.; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Staff meetings. Materials and minutes., 1960-1962; 1976-1978.; 5 folders (Box 3)